<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<resources>
    <chapterdata>
        <id>351</id>
        <name>Java versions and Java 8</name>
    </chapterdata>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        Java has undergone many changes since its release. Take a look at this version table from
        <i>Wikipedia</i>:
        ]]>
    </text>
    <image name="java_versions"/>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        Here is what may change in a new release:
        ]]>
    </text>
    <title text="Deprecate obsolete classes"/>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        Deprecating a method or a class means marking it for removal in a future version. In most cases,
        a suitable replacement is given. Deprecated code can still be used, however, it's recommended to
        use the replacement instead.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <boxed title="Annotation">
        <![CDATA[
        Deprecated code is marked with the <b>@Deprecated</b> annotation. Your compiler will raise a
        warning if you use such a method or class.
        ]]>
    </boxed>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        For example much of the class <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/util/Date.html">java.util.Date</a> has been deprecated, because a better alternative
        has been added in Java 7, called the <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/time/package-summary.html">java.time</a> package.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <title text="Extend the standard library"/>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        In each version, new classes, methods and sometimes even entire packages are added to the standard
        library. These could be:
        ]]>
    </text>
    <list>
        <![CDATA[
        <ul>
        <li>Better implementations of previously present code (in this case, the previous code is ofter deprecated).</li>
        <li>Code that brings some entirely new functionality.
        </ul>
        ]]>
    </list>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        For example, in Java 7, the package <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/nio/package-summary.html">java.nio</a>
        package was added (the name stands for New IO).
        ]]>
    </text>
    <code><![CDATA[
        
        <font color="#E65100">try</font> {
<br/>	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="#999900">List</font>&lt;<font color="#999900">String</font>> lines = <font color="#999900">Files</font>.<font color="#ADD8E6">readAllLines</font>(<font color="#999900">Paths</font>.<font color="#ADD8E6">get</font>(<font color="#2E8B57">"myfile.txt"</font>));
<br/>} <font color="#E65100">catch</font>(<font color="#999900">IOException</font> e) {
<br/>	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="#999900">System</font>.<font color="#ADD8E6">err</font>.<font color="#ADD8E6">println</font>(<font color="#2E8B57">"<font color="</font>#999900">Failed to read from file!"</font>);
<br/>}
        
    ]]></code>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        Before the <i>NIO</i> package, programmers had to use readers and loops to achieve this.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <title text="Extend the language itself"/>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        These are the most significant changes. New keywords and structures may be introduced, and the syntax
        of Java can change, allowing the programmer to be more productive.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <boxed title="Java 5: Generics">
        <![CDATA[
        For instance, Java 5 introduced generics, which was a significant extension to Java.
        ]]>
    </boxed>
    <title text="Why Java 8?"/>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        This course is about Java 8. However, if you take a look at the version table again, you'll notice that
        it is not at all the latest release. So, what makes it so significant that it deserves its own course?
        ]]>
    </text>
    <boxed title="The most widely used">
        <![CDATA[
        Java 8 became the most widely used version, despite the newer releases. This is partly because it offered
        so many new things, and partly because the newer version did not, so many programmers and companies simply did not consider
        worth their time to upgrade.
        ]]>
    </boxed>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        In the following chapters, we'll take a look at the most important changes of Java 8, with detailed explanations
        and examples!
        ]]>
    </text>
</resources>
